Well, a game is coming together quite nicely, but I think you can see the clear problem here, which
is that, well, if we miss the header it just keeps on going.
And this makes for some rather easy gameplay.
There's just no real challenge.
So in this lesson we will be looking at how we can end our game when we miss the header.
If you move over to the control group, you may have noticed the special block over here with the word
stop all.
And I think there is no explanation required for what this does.
As I'm sure you can guess, this block stops all.
For example, if I play the script and then click this block, notice how the game comes to a halt.
So the block is clearly doing its job.
It is stopping all the scripts in all the sprites.
But just like the other blocks, we can change what it does by clicking here.
So instead of stopping or we could just stop this script.
So basically whatever script we put this block into, it'll stop that script when the script reaches
this code block.
Alternatively, we can also stop other scripts in the sprite and as the name states, every other script
in the sprite except for this one will stop.
There is one other important aspect I want you to look at.
But basically notice how right now this is just like a normal code block.
However, if I change it to stop this script or all see how the code block changes and there is no indent
at the bottom.
So basically this means there can be no code under this block.
You'll see if we try.
It just doesn't connect.
And if you think about it, it makes perfect sense.
Because if we stop all or stop the script, the code under it would never run anyway.
So it doesn't make sense to be able to add any code underneath it.
Well, now that you understand how the stop block works, I'm going to give you quite a tricky challenge.
I think you're up to it.
So I want you to, in a moment, to pause the video and to see if you can get the game to stop when
the ball touches the ground.
Now, remember, this is going to require a lot of logical thinking or thinking outside the box, but
give it a shot.
Can you get the game to pause to stop when the ball touches the ground?
Write, pause, think and try.
Well, if you actually managed to get this working, that is amazing.
But even if you didn't, that's also great because this is where the learning happens in trying to figure
things out.
This is where you really have lots of fun.
So let's see how it could be done.
Let's look at two different ways we can get this done.
First things first, we're going to need one of our when start forever and if combo packs.
So I'll just duplicate this one and just get rid of the code inside.
And then I will duplicate it again because we are covering two methods.
Now, the first method we're going to think about a bit is quite, quite a bit out of the box.
I don't know if you came up with this one, but if you did, that's great.
And we're going to go down to the sensing group.
Look at this option touching color.
So that's cool.
We can check if our sprite is touching a specific color.
Hmm.
Interesting.
The only problem is what color do we check for?
Because the bottom is all pretty much the same color.
Well let's change that.
So clicking on our backdrop and then going to this editor, notice how there are a bunch of tools that
you can use to customize it.
But all we need is a specific color at the bottom.
So to do this, I can just use this tool.
Choose a unique color and draw a line at the bottom.
And there you have it.
Now I can change the touching to this color by using the color picker.
And finally add in my stop all.
Now when we play the game and then when we miss.
Our game stops.
It's great.
That works, and that was a creative way of solving this problem.
But before I move on, I'm going to show you another method.
But it'll be quick.
So as you can see here, I have already assembled the script and if we play the game, you'll see it
works just the same and doesn't even need the touching color.
Looking at the script, you can see that it checks if the y position of the ball is less than -150,
which basically means it's touching the ground.
And if it is, well, it stops too easy.
So both of these methods would work.
And sometimes we need creative ways to do things.
But if we think even more we might find a way that is even easier.
So always keep thinking.
And that's basically it.
Your game is ready to play, and the upcoming lessons will be making it a lot more fun with score and
levels.
But for now, just appreciate how far you have come with this game that you've built.
Play it for a bit and have some fun.